Welcome!
In this brief video, we will be discussing
decision making without probabilities where
cost is involved.
We will cover the Optimistic or Maximax approach,
the Conservative or Maximin approach,
and also the Minimax Regret approach.
We will be using this payoff table where Payoffs are costs.
The approach we will use in this tutorial
is applicable to all cases where smaller payoff
values are preferred over larger ones.
The objective could be to minimize cost, minimize
customer waiting time, minimize risk, minimize
distance, and so on.
The Optimistic or Maximax Approach
Using this approach we choose the alternative
with the best of the best payoffs. Note that
the payoffs are costs, therefore the smaller
the better. For d1 , the best payoff is -5
For d2 , the best is -9
and for d3, the best is -5.
The overall best is -9.
Therefore the optimistic decision is to choose d2.
The Conservative or Maximin Approach
Using this approach, we choose the alternative
that has best of the worst payoffs.
We first choose the worst payoff in each alternative,
and then choose the best of them.
Since these are costs, for d1, the worst is
for d2 , the worst is 15
and for d3, the worst is 18.
The best of these worst payoffs is 14
Therefore the conservative decision is to choose d1.
The Minimax Regret Approach
Using this approach, we choose the alternative
with the minimum of all the maximum regrets
across all alternatives.
Regret is the difference between the best
payoff and the actual payoff received in a
particular state of nature.
Therefore for s1 the best payoff is 5 since
we are dealing with costs.
That is, if you knew s1 was going to occur,
you would have chosen d3.
So if s1 occurs and you already chose d1,
your regret will be 12 – 5 = 7.
That is, if you could pay $5 for an item and
you paid $12 instead, your regret will be $7
Note that if these are profits, we will subtract
all payoffs from the best, which in that case
would be the largest value. But because they
are costs, we will subtract the smallest from
other payoffs. Whatever you do, make sure
your regret values are not negative.
So going back to s1
If instead you chose d2, you’re paying $15
when you could pay $5 and your regret will
be 15 – 5 which equals 10.
And if you chose d3, your regret is 5 – 5
which equals 0. That is, there is no regret.
For s2 your best payoff is -5.
So if you chose d1, your regret will be -5
minus -5 which equals 0 → no regret.
Note that the double negative becomes positive.
And you if you chose d2, your regret is 11
minus -5 which equals 16.
If you chose d3, your regret will be 18 minus
-5 which equals 23.
If s3 occurs, the best payoff is -9.
So if you chose d1, your regret will be 14
minus -9 which gives 23.
And you if you chose d2, your regret is -9
minus -9 which equals 0.
If you chose d3, your regret will be -5 minus
-9 which equals 4
Here is the Regret Table.
Note that after regrets are calculated, the
approach for determining the best alternative
is exactly the same for profit and cost problems.
Since the decision is to be made based on
minimax regret, we first determine the maximum
regret for each alternative, and then choose
the minimum.
For d1, the maximum regret is 23,
for d2, the maximum is 16,
for d3, the maximum regret is 23.
The minimum of these maximum regrets is 16.
Therefore the minimax regret decision is to
choose d2.
Please leave your comments or questions below.
Thanks for watching.